Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Catherine.
我是Catherine。
And today we have a very advanced lesson for you all about medicine.
今天我们为大家带来一堂关于医学的高级课程。
That's right.
没错。
Today we're going to take a look at what is very widely known as Chinese traditional medicine.
今天我们要探讨一个广为人知的话题——中医。
So a very interesting topic in general.
所以总的来说，这是个非常有趣的话题。
That's right.
没错。
And for people who use this, they might call it TCM, traditional Chinese medicine.
对于使用它的人来说，他们可能会称之为TCM，即传统中医。
So remember that there's that acronym as well.
所以记住还有这个缩写。
But let's take a listen to today's dialogue and when we come back, we'll be discussing
我们先来听听今天的对话，等回来后再讨论
some of the important words and phrases in the dialogue.
对话中的一些重要词汇和短语。
What's wrong?
怎么了？
I have a headache.
我头疼。
These past few days I've been living off painkillers.
这几天我一直靠止痛药撑着。
Man, I feel like my head is going to explode.
天哪，我感觉我的头要炸了。
You should get acupuncture treatment.
你应该试试针灸治疗。
My mom was always having headache issues and it was acupuncture that cured her.
我妈妈以前经常头疼，是针灸治好了她。
The results are too slow.
效果太慢了。
On top of that, just the thought of smoking needles poking into my flesh frightens me.
而且，一想到冒着烟的针扎进我的肉里，我就害怕。
They don't just randomly stick you.
他们不会随便乱扎你。
They find your pressure points.
他们会找到你的穴位。
The heat allows the body to immediately respond to the treatment, restoring the body's qi.
热量能让身体立即对治疗产生反应，恢复体内的气。
But I get scared the moment I see a needle.
但我一看到针就害怕。
How could I stand having needles in my body for hours on end?
我怎么能忍受身上扎着针好几个小时呢？
The needles are very thin.
针非常细。
And as long as the doctor's technique is good and the patient himself is relaxed, it won't
只要医生的手法好，病人自己放松，
hurt.
就不会疼。
On the contrary, it will actually alleviate pain.
相反，它实际上能缓解疼痛。
Now there are high-tech needles that are micro-thin.
现在有高科技的微细针。
They don't hurt at all.
它们一点也不疼。
However, if you are really scared of acupuncture, scraping or cupping are also options.
不过，如果你真的害怕针灸，刮痧或拔罐也是选择。
Scraping is too terrifying.
刮痧太吓人了。
When they finish scraping, your body is all red as if you were just tortured.
刮完以后，身上红红的，就像被折磨过一样。
Cupping is the same.
拔罐也一样。
Your body ends up with red circles all over it.
身上全是红圈。
It looks like someone beat you up.
看起来像被人打了一顿。
This only signifies that the toxins have left the body.
这只表示毒素已经排出体外了。
Actually, there's only discomfort during the treatment process.
其实，只是治疗过程中有点不舒服。
Once it's over, you'll feel very comfortable.
结束后，你会感觉很舒服。
Chinese medicine is strange.
中医真奇怪。
The patients are already ill and then the doctor makes them suffer more.
病人已经病了，医生还让他们更难受。
This is the only way to get at the problem.
这是解决问题的唯一办法。
Anyway, if you want to relieve the pain, you are just going to have to be tough and do
总之，如果你想缓解疼痛，就得坚强点，然后去
it.
做。
Forget it.
算了吧。
I don't want to inflict any more pain on myself.
我不想再给自己增加痛苦了。
In a little while, I'll go and buy some more painkillers and take a nap.
过一会儿，我去买些止痛药，然后睡一觉。
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So now obviously we are talking about what is commonly known as alternative medicine
所以现在我们显然在谈论通常所说的替代医学，
because we know that traditional medicine nowadays is doctors, you have antibiotics,
因为我们知道现代传统医学是医生、抗生素
that sort of thing.
之类的东西。
And here you're actually using these techniques and these different ways of curing someone.
而这里你实际上是在用这些技术和不同的方法来治疗某人。
So the first thing that comes to mind here is acupuncture.
所以首先想到的就是针灸。
That's right.
没错。
So acupuncture is usually considered a part of Chinese medicine and it's a kind of medicine
针灸通常被认为是中医的一部分，它是一种
that uses needles in different parts of the body.
在身体不同部位使用针的医学。
So it might look really scary because you see people lying on their stomachs with needles
所以它可能看起来很吓人，因为你看到人们趴着，背上
coming out of their backs.
插着针。
And the places where they put the needles in, they're called pressure points, right?
他们扎针的地方叫做穴位，对吧？
That's right.
没错。
And pressure points are things that we talk about with massages as well.
而压力点也是我们在谈论按摩时会提到的概念。
So a good masseuse, a person who does a massage, will also look for these pressure points,
所以一个好的按摩师，也就是做按摩的人，也会寻找这些压力点，
which are key points on the body.
这些是身体上的关键点。
And in acupuncture, they'll put these needles into those points as well because each point
在针灸中，他们也会把针扎在这些点上，因为每个点
relates to a different part of the body, like the liver or the kidneys.
都与身体的不同部位相关，比如肝脏或肾脏。
Right.
对。
So it's actually very interesting, the fact that by sticking a needle in one of these
所以这其实非常有趣，通过把针扎进其中一个
pressure points, they are curing or alleviating the pain of maybe, like you say, your kidney
压力点，他们就能治愈或缓解疼痛，比如你说的肾脏
or your liver or something like this.
或肝脏之类的疼痛。
This is a really great word though, Marco, the word that you just used, to alleviate
不过，马可，你刚才用的这个词真的很棒，就是“缓解”
pain.
疼痛。
Now to alleviate pain means to make the pain go away.
“缓解疼痛”的意思就是让疼痛消失。
So we heard the opposite of that as well, also at the very end of today's dialogue.
我们在今天对话的结尾也听到了它的反义词。
So the opposite of alleviate would be to inflict pain.
所以“缓解”的反义词是“施加”疼痛。
This is to do pain to yourself or to someone else.
这是指对自己或他人造成疼痛。
To cause pain.
引起疼痛。
So to alleviate is to take it away and to inflict is to cause.
所以“缓解”是消除疼痛，而“施加”是引起疼痛。
So now acupuncture is very popular.
所以现在针灸非常流行。
Sticking needles in people's pressure points, it does seem like it would hurt, but there
把针扎进人的穴位，看起来确实会很疼，但还有
are other ones that maybe are not as widely known.
其他一些可能不那么广为人知的方法。
The next one that we're going to talk about is scraping.
接下来我们要讨论的是刮痧。
Scraping.
刮痧。
So to scrape is a verb and you can scrape the bottom of your plate with your spoon or
所以“刮”是一个动词，你可以用勺子刮盘子的底部，或者
you can scrape on, you know, sometimes cats like to scrape on the furniture.
你可以刮，你知道，有时候猫喜欢在家具上刮。
They use their claws and make that sound.
它们用爪子弄出那种声音。
But in this case, scraping is a little bit more maybe painful sounding.
但在这里，刮痧听起来可能更疼一些。
What do they do in scraping?
刮痧是怎么做的？
So basically it's the same thing.
基本上是一回事。
They use different tools and they scrape your body.
他们用不同的工具，然后刮你的身体。
They just, I don't know, basically what I understand from it is that they are extracting
他们只是，我不知道，我理解的大概是，他们通过
the illness by taking it out of your skin.
把病从皮肤里提取出来。
So they use what looks like a small knife or like a flat kind of sharp blade.
所以他们用一种看起来像小刀或扁平锋利刀片的东西。
And they actually kind of take off the top layer of your skin.
然后他们实际上会去掉你皮肤的表层。
They scrape it away.
把它刮掉。
It's very, very painful from what I've heard.
据我所知，这非常非常疼。
I've never done it myself, but as we see in the dialogue, it does look very, it looks
我自己没试过，但就像我们在对话中看到的，它看起来确实很，看起来
like you've been hit or treated poorly at the prison or something because your skin
像你被打过或在监狱里被虐待过一样，因为你的皮肤
is red and almost bleeding.
是红的，几乎在流血。
That's right.
没错。
And another one that actually looks quite painful when you see someone after they've
还有一种方法，当你看到别人做完后，看起来真的很疼，
done it is called cupping.
叫做拔罐。
Right.
对。
Now, this one you might have seen even in the last Karate Kid movie.
这个你可能在上一部《功夫梦》电影里见过。
Basically it's a little round bulb or a little round glass cup and the doctor, the Chinese
基本上是一个小圆球或小圆玻璃杯，医生，中国
doctor will light a piece of cotton and will put the cup over it and the suction effect
医生会点燃一块棉花，然后把杯子盖在上面，通过
that by putting out the fire and it sucks up all the oxygen and everything causes the
灭火产生的吸力效应，它会吸走所有氧气和一切，导致
cup to suck onto your skin really, really tight.
杯子非常紧地吸在你的皮肤上。
You put it on your skin so it creates a vacuum, right?
你把它放在皮肤上，这样就形成了一个真空，对吧？
Exactly.
完全正确。
There's no air coming in.
没有空气进入。
And that way the cup that there's no air in has to pull out all those chemicals and those
这样，没有空气的杯子就必须把那些化学物质、
toxins and that oil from your skin and take it away.
毒素和油脂从你的皮肤里吸出来并带走。
Right.
对。
So it's actually pulling at your skin.
所以它实际上是在拉扯你的皮肤。
Yeah.
是的。
And well, that's the thing with the vacuum effect is so great and pulling it out with
嗯，这就是真空效应的厉害之处，它以如此大的力量
such force that you're actually left with a big purple or red circle on your skin from
把它吸出来，以至于你的皮肤上会留下一个大紫色或红色的圆圈，
I guess the blood clot type thing that is caused by it.
我想是因为它引起的血块之类的东西。
So you will see a person's back maybe and they have bruises.
所以你会看到一个人的背上可能有瘀伤。
Bruises.
瘀伤。
Yeah, like six, seven, ten bruises on their backs.
是的，像六个、七个、十个瘀伤在他们的背上。
Although I am told that even though it's very painful and it looks even more painful, the
虽然我听说，即使它很疼，而且看起来更疼，但
effect is that it does help your circulation.
效果是它确实有助于你的血液循环。
It helps the blood in your body move around more freely.
它帮助你体内的血液更自由地流动。
Yeah, I've heard the same thing.
是的，我也听说过同样的事。
And even though that it looks painful and it may be painful while they're doing it,
而且即使它看起来疼，做的时候可能也疼，
I've heard that after it's done, even though it looks like it should hurt, it looks like
我听说做完之后，即使它看起来应该疼，看起来像
a bruise, it doesn't hurt like a bruise.
瘀伤，但它不像瘀伤那样疼。
So people don't actually say, oh, you know, don't touch my back.
所以人们实际上不会说，哦，你知道，别碰我的背。
It really hurts.
真的很疼。
It doesn't really seem that way.
实际上似乎不是那样。
Well, and there's an interesting line in the dialogue that is related to this.
嗯，对话中有一句有趣的话与此相关。
It's about scraping actually, but you can say it about cupping as well.
实际上是关于刮痧的，但你也可以用它来形容拔罐。
Your body is all red as if you were just tortured.
你的身体全红了，好像你刚被折磨过一样。
Now as if you were tortured or we could say as if you were beaten up.
就像你被折磨过一样，或者我们可以说就像你被揍过一样。
And in this case, was the person tortured?
在这种情况下，那个人被折磨了吗？
No.
没有。
It's basically a relation or making that relation that your skin is so, let's say bloody that
这基本上是一种关联，或者说建立一种关联，你的皮肤如此，比如说血淋淋，
it looks as if you were tortured.
看起来就像你被折磨过一样。
So it seems like somebody hit you with a whip or something.
所以看起来好像有人用鞭子之类的东西打了你。
It looks like you were tortured, but you weren't.
看起来你被折磨过，但实际上你没有。
So as if is a way for us to make a comparison or an analogy.
所以“as if”是我们用来做比较或类比的一种方式。
Right.
对。
I think you can see it in maybe books, you know, so maybe you would describe a guy saying,
我想你可能在书里见过，你知道，所以你可能描述一个人说，
oh, he was really angry as if he had rabies.
哦，他非常生气，好像得了狂犬病一样。
Yeah, it's as if he had rabies like he doesn't, but he's acting like he does.
是的，就像他得了狂犬病一样，但他没有，但他的行为像得了。
Or maybe you run into the kitchen and eat so much food as if you hadn't eaten in days.
或者你可能冲进厨房，吃了那么多食物，好像好几天没吃饭一样。
Exactly.
完全正确。
So you have obviously, but you're acting like someone who is starving.
所以你显然有，但你的行为像一个饿着的人。
So yeah, that is an interesting way to describe or to make a connection between two different
所以是的，这是一种有趣的方式来描述或连接两个不同
things.
的事物。
And well, Chinese traditional medicine as well, a very interesting and historical form
嗯，中医也是一种非常有趣且历史悠久的
of treating illnesses.
治疗疾病的方式。
Now I'm told that it does work, even though some people are very skeptical about it.
我听说它确实有效，尽管有些人对此非常怀疑。
And I don't think it's accepted in the international medical field.
而且我认为它在国际医学领域不被接受。
Well, I think that there's a Western medicine which has its benefits.
嗯，我认为西医有它的好处。
You know, you have penicillin and all of these different antibiotics to help us combat different
你知道，你有青霉素和所有这些不同的抗生素来帮助我们对抗不同的
diseases and bacteria.
疾病和细菌。
But also traditional Chinese medicine kind of helps other things.
但中医也能帮助其他方面。
I think there is a spirituality, this idea that we have a chi, there are positive and
我认为其中有一种灵性，就是我们拥有“气”的概念，身体里有正负
negative forces in our bodies, and sometimes trauma or big events will make that chi kind
力量，有时创伤或重大事件会让这种“气”变得
of, well, it'll affect it in a bad way.
嗯，会以不好的方式影响它。
So the chi is unbalanced.
所以“气”就不平衡了。
And so a lot of this is about rebalancing your system.
因此很多治疗都是为了重新平衡你的系统。
And if you believe that and you really understand that there are certain forces inside your
如果你相信这一点，并且真正理解身体里有某些力量，
body, then I'm sure this kind of medicine has a positive effect on you.
那么我确信这种医学对你会有积极效果。
Right.
没错。
I believe that it does have its ups and downs.
我相信它有好有坏。
I was very skeptical about it until once, actually, I had a very, very bad headache
我以前对此非常怀疑，直到有一次，我头痛得非常厉害，
and somebody took and pushed a pressure point on my finger, on my thumb for about maybe
有人按了我手指上的一个穴位，大概按了
one or two minutes and the headache was gone.
一两分钟，头痛就消失了。
So I was very much amazed.
所以我非常惊讶。
But at the same time, when people are treated maybe for, you know, maybe they can conceive
但同时，当人们接受治疗，比如为了怀孕，
a baby and they're doing these rituals or giving them ginger or different roots to drink
他们进行一些仪式，或者给他们喝姜汤或不同的根茎
and eat and stuff.
来吃或喝。
I don't know if that really does help or what evidence there is that it actually does work.
我不知道这真的有没有帮助，或者有什么证据证明它确实有效。
Well, I think that's something that also is important to look at on an individual basis.
嗯，我认为这也是需要根据个人情况来看的。
I don't think even some Western medicines help all the time if you're not in a place
我觉得即使是一些西药，如果你不
where you believe that it will work.
相信它会有效，也不一定总能起作用。
But the interesting aspect of it is, of course, so many years ago, we're talking about hundreds
但有趣的是，当然，很多年前，我们说的是几百
or thousands of years ago, when there was no Western medicine and then people were being
或几千年前，当时没有西医，人们却通过
cured and treated by these techniques, which actually worked.
这些确实有效的技术被治愈和治疗。
So there is a very interesting aspect that maybe even Western medicine can learn from
所以有一个非常有趣的方面，也许连西医都可以从
traditional medicine like this.
这样的传统医学中学习。
Definitely.
确实如此。
So it's an interesting topic, Oriental medicine, Western medicine, but we want to know what
所以这是一个有趣的话题，东方医学、西方医学，但我们想知道
you think about it.
你的看法。
We also want to know in your home country, do you have a traditional kind of medicine
我们也想知道，在你的祖国，有没有传统的医学
or any medical alternatives to Western medicine?
或西医之外的替代疗法？
Let us know, our website is EnglishPod.com.
告诉我们，我们的网站是 EnglishPod.com。
All right, we'll see you guys there.
好了，我们那里见。
Bye.
再见。
This is Mike with modern medicine.
我是迈克，代表现代医学。